<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Antarctic Journal]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Antarctic Journal]]></description>
        <link>https://thegrid.ai/antarctic-journal/</link>
        <generator>The Grid</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Feb 2016 00:08:53 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://thegrid.ai/antarctic-journal/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Day 1 - Departure Day]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<article><h1>Day 1 - Departure Day</h1><p>NOTE: Sorry about all the footnotes. Future entries will not be so densely annotated.]

Got up almost immediately and showered, and made last-minute checks. Got to the ship about 8:30am and met So[1] carrying a huge monitor. Got a bit lost on my way down to my cabin - a four-berth quite forward, on the port side, and thankfully with a porthole. Saw Simon J and we pondered the fact that our cage pallets were still on the dockside. But they still seemed confident of leaving at 5pm.</p></article>]]></description>
            <link>https://thegrid.ai/antarctic-journal/day-1-departure-day/index.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">ae12d79f-b325-4551-b6f3-40e1861e6d19</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 23 Feb 2016 00:08:44 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[In 1998 I went to Antarctica.]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<article><h1>In 1998 I went to Antarctica.</h1><p>Why? Fair question. I wanted to see it with my own eyes. I wanted to hear the silence calling[1], to paraphrase Douglas Mawson. I wanted to gaze upon the vast white vistas at the seat of the world.

Actually, no. That’s a bit melodramatic and it wasn’t really like that. It was achingly practical. Antarctica didn’t “call” to me across the Southern Ocean. There is no explorer DNA hardcoded into my genes. But, as the name suggests, Antarctica is where Antarctic krill live, and I should really see where they hang out if I wanted to study them, which I did. And bring a few back, of course. But on top of all that, I did want to go. Not a life’s ambition, not the realisation of a dream. But an opportunity not to be missed.

It was 1998, the first time. I was a little while into a PhD project looking at Antarctic krill. Krill are basically whale food; shrimp-like crustaceans that drift around the Southern Ocean, mostly getting caught in baleen and guzzled down by sea birds. They’re a keystone species, meaning they eat pretty much anything smaller than they are, and get eaten by anything larger. I was interested in whether the hole in the ozone layer (remember that?) could harm krill populations. Short answer? The krill are fine. But I needed to do a lot of experiments, and they needed krill. And I couldn’t get them at the pet store.

Antarctic krill B&W line drawing
Antarctic krill (Euphausia superba). What it's all about.
So of I went, congenitally naïve and uncharacteristically ready for adventure. And this, along with about old school 35mm Kodachrome 500 slides, lots of Emails and a crate full of memories, is the result. I kept a diary[2] every day, a record of what I did and what I had done to me, what I saw, what I heard, tasted, felt. What I experienced.

I hope it is of some interest.</p></article>]]></description>
            <link>https://thegrid.ai/antarctic-journal/in-1998-i-went-to-antarctica/index.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">b153177c-ab3e-4b39-84c3-e8f483d9c7fa</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 22 Feb 2016 23:35:43 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>